[soft, low rumbling]
[heartbeat thumping softly]
[heartbeat grows louder]
[heartbeat fades]
[Amélie] In the beginning,
there was nothing.
[gentle music]
Nothing except God.
[heartbeat thumping]
How long had God been around?
No one's old enough to say.
Anyway, the universe was
rather empty, as you can see.
But that was fine, 'cause
God didn't look at anything
or want anything.
God wasn't interested
in anything.
God didn't even care
about being God.
It might be best
to think of God as a tube.
Yes, a tube.
Allow me to explain.
All God ever did was
swallow, digest, and eject.
God's divine sustenance
came in and went out.
But God retained nothing.
Just like a tube.
[music fades]
The eyes of living beings
possess the most
remarkable properties.
The gaze.
[doctor] Hmm, hmm.
[Amélie] We don't say that
the ears have a listener...
[bright music]
[fingers snapping]
[Amélie] ...or that the nose
has a smeller or a sniffer,
but the eyes have a gaze.
What's the difference between
the eyes that have a gaze
and eyes that don't?
There's a word for it:
life.
God did not have a gaze.
[doctor] Hmm.
I'm afraid
your child is a vegetable.
[Amélie]
Alarming, wouldn't you think?
But the child's parents
were the optimistic sort.
And to be honest,
as things stood,
they didn't seem to mind
this development.
You see, they already
had two children,
two children who were
very, very much alive.
[kids grunt, giggle]
[music continues]
[Amélie] So a quiet,
little plant like this one
was a gift, really.
That was God's greatest power.
God was unflappable.
Not all the pilgrims
who came to pay homage,
not all the tickling,
not volcanoes,
not even the most
ecstatic music.
Nothing could faze God.
[clapping]
[Amélie] I know humans
who would pay dearly
for such a power,
the power of serenity.
[bright music resumes]
[Amélie] Still, everyone wanted
God to show signs of life,
of movement,
of anything at all, really.
But all God did was
keep on doing nothing.
So little by little,
people lost interest in God
until God was almost
forgotten about completely.
Days, weeks, centuries passed.
[music continues]
Stop! That's it.
What happened that day
remains a mystery.
[dramatic music]
[Amélie] Some people deny
the role of accidents
in evolution.
They want a reason
for everything,
but sometimes all it takes
is a speck of dust.
Just the tiniest,
little speck of dust...
-[water rushing]
-...to change everything.
[muffled]
♪ Happy Birthday, dear Amélie ♪
[Patrick laughs]
I'll blow out the candles.
No, it's my turn.
-[rumbling, objects rattling]
-What's happening?
Mama, I'm scared.
Don't panic.
It's only a little earthquake,
they happen a lot
-here in Japan.
-[rapid heartbeat thumping]
[objects rattling]
[Andre shouts] Papa!
[stammering]
Quick, kids, under the table!
[explosion booms]
[dramatic music]
[Amélie] God was finally
endowed with gaze
and a body too.
What could God do now?
-Was this a good thing?
-[gasps]
[whooshing]
[Amélie thuds]
[all gasp]
Are you okay, baby?
[Amélie] Baby?
Who was this baby?
God wasn't a baby.
God immediately spoke up
to set the record straight,
declaring,
in God's celestial tone...
[Amélie babbles]
[family laughs]
Ah! That's right.
[kids laughing]
[Patrick babbles]
[laughing mockingly]
-[Juliette laughs]
-[Danièèle] It's a miracle.
-[Amélie whines]
-That was wonderful, sweetie.
-[Amélie] No, it wasn't.
-[Juliette continues laughing]
[Amélie]
It wasn't wonderful at all.
-Bravo, sweetheart!
-[Amélie] Their lips move
and words come out.
-[Andre] She talks like a baby!
-[Amélie] When God's lips move,
-only noise comes out.
-[Danièle speaks indistinctly]
[Amélie whimpers]
[screaming]
Uh, what do we do?
Oh, uh...oh, wait,
I got it, I'll call my mom.
What? Patrick!
[screaming continues]
[Amélie]
It wasn't for lack of trying,
but all God could do
was scream in despair.
God's body was a prison.
[rake rustles]
[Amélie screaming in distance]
[gentle somber music]
[glass shatters]
[muffled screaming continues]
[Andre] Mom, she's throwing
her toys again!
[Juliette] It went
right through the window!
Andre! Stop it!
[Andre]
I'll stop it when she stops it!
[Juliette]
Mom, she took my things again!
-[Danièle] Juliette, please.
-[Amélie shrieks]
[Andre]
I'm sick and tired of this!
[Amélie wails]
[Patrick gasps]
[Andre shouting indistinctly]
Ohayo, gozaimasu.
[kids screaming]
-[Danièle] Andre!
-[Juliette] I'm gonna get you!
-[Juliette shouts] Give it back!
-[Amélie screaming]
Arigato, Kashima-san.
-Care to come in?
-[indistinct shouting]
Sorry, we're in a little
over our heads today.
-[Juliette] No! That's mine!
-[Amélie shrieks]
[Juliette shouts]
[kids shouting]
[objects clattering]
[Danièle sighs heavily]
[Amélie screaming]
[Danièle] I can't take it
anymore, this is impossible.
I can't rehearse for my concert,
and what about you?
You don't even
resemble a diplomat.
[Patrick chuckles]
Guess who brought this back?
Oh, no.
Oh yes, our dear landlady.
She scared me half to death.
It's like she was lurking
out there waiting for me.
She saw the window?
What's she going to think of us?
[Patrick] She knows a girl
who could help us out.
The girl's family served hers
before the war.
-[Andre shouts]
-I'm so embarrassed.
[impacts crash]
[gasps]
[kids shout]
That's a good idea,
give her a call.
[kids shouting indistinctly]
[door slides open, shut]
[doorbell chimes]
[Danièle]
Can you see who that is?
[Patrick]
Yeah, yeah, I've got it.
Ohayo, Nish--
-Mother?
-[gentle music]
That's right.
It's good to see you.
But, wha--what are you--
Though I think you were really
expecting this young woman.
[chuckles]
Oh, Nishio-san.
-[Andre and Juliette] Granny!
-Oh, my little darlings,
how big you've grown.
My tooth is loose, look.
-[babbling]
-Ugh!
[laughs] What a killer smile.
-[laughs]
-Who is that lady?
[Patrick] Mother, kids,
this is Nishio-san.
She's gonna help us out
around here.
Please, come in.
Dozo, dozo, this way.
Oh, I'll take care of those.
[Juliette] Granny, did you
bring us any chocolates?
-[Granny] Yes, I did.
-[Juliette] Ooh, thanks.
-[Andre] And comic books?
-[Granny] Why, of course.
[music continues]
You don't look so well, sweetie.
We'd given up expecting you.
-It's been so long.
-There was so much to do
getting ready for the visit.
Just look at this suit.
Isn't it perfect?
-[Patrick] It's been six months.
-[Juliette] Wow.
Oh, hi there, I'm Danièle.
I really appreciate
you helping us out.
[gasps] Your mother's here?
Hello, my de--
You look a little
frazzled as well.
[Amélie shrieks]
[Danièle and Patrick gasp]
Ah, is that my little treasure?
-[Andre panting]
-[Juliette] Come on.
[Patrick mutters]
More like a little monster.
Nishio-san,
let me show you around.
It's changed a lot
since you were young.
[raspy breathing]
[intriguing music]
-[Amélie gasps]
-[Andre] In here.
-[Juliette] Ready?
-[Granny] Ready.
[Amélie gasps]
-[whispers] Look in the bed.
-[Granny chuckles]
[music continues]
You wait right here,
children, let me handle this.
[kids whimper]
[Amélie growls]
Hello there.
Mmm. I'm your grandmother.
-It's nice to finally meet--
-[Amélie snarls]
Oh, aren't you crabby?
Wait, I know just what you need.
-[growling]
-I always carry one of these
-in my bag.
-[gasps]
[Granny] A little pick me up.
[gasps]
This is white chocolate
from Belgium,
-where you come from.
-[Amélie sniffs]
[growls]
[Granny] Go on, try it.
[music intensifies]
[sparkling chime rings]
[upbeat music]
[Amélie] A miracle transpired.
[energy whooshes]
[Juliette] Mama, Papa!
[Andre] Come and see!
[Patrick] What's happened?
[Patrick gasps]
[gentle music]
[Amélie]
The joy of white chocolate
showed me that God was me.
[all gasping]
Meet my good friend Amélie.
[Amélie]
And that's how I was born
at the age of two and a half
in the heart of
the Konsai Mountains,
under the gaze of
my paternal grandmother,
and by the grace
of white chocolate.
[Danièle gasps]
[music continues]
[yawns]
This calls for champagne,
don't you think?
[parents sigh]
[Amélie] I had become joy.
Wherever joy was to be found,
there you would find me too.
[Amélie pants]
[panting continues]
[upbeat music]
[Amélie giggling]
Joy had finally brought
my body to life.
Chocolate awakened
all my senses.
In mere days, I made up
for all the lost time,
though I didn't really
think of that time
as having been lost.
Apparently humans should know
how to walk by two and a half.
[Amélie giggling]
Walking wasn't
all that complicated.
You fall forward,
catch yourself, and repeat.
[music continues]
But then there was running.
[Amélie panting]
Running is escape.
[Amélie squeals]
It's the verb of
bandits and superheroes.
Whoa!
[music continues]
[Amélie pants]
[Amélie]
But it's more exhausting.
[panting]
Most importantly,
by age two and a half,
humans are supposed
to know how to talk.
[inhales] Ah--
[vacuum whirs]
[whirring continues]
[curious music]
[Amélie] What was this strange,
long-necked creature?
And how was it able
to do what it did,
to take something
and leave nothing?
[gasps]
[whirring continues]
[Amélie] Only a God could
perform such a miracle.
What could be more divine
than this pure and
simple annihilation?
[music continues]
[particles whir]
I knew then that
I had a brother.
[Danièle] Come away, Amélie,
Nishio-san needs to use that--
Vacuum cleaner.
[Danièle gasps]
-[Andre] Snack time.
-[Juliette] Wait for me.
[Danièle] Patrick, Patrick!
Amélie just said her first word!
[Patrick gasps]
That's wonderful, what was it?
Vacuum cleaner.
Vacuum cleaner?
What a lovely word!
Bravo, Amélie.
[Juliette chuckles]
Try another word, Amélie.
Try saying Ma-ma.
[Amélie] Well, clearly
this meant a lot to them.
-Mama.
-[all gasp]
[Danièle] Very good, Amélie!
That's me, Mama!
It's my turn now, my turn.
Pa...pa!
-Papa.
-That's right, sweetie.
Bravo! Papa!
[Amélie]
What a strange reaction.
-[Danièle laughs]
-[Amélie] It was as if
they needed me
to say their names
to prove they existed.
Oh, cut it out!
Juliette.
[gasps] She said my name.
She said Juliette.
[bright upbeat music]
[Danièle gasps]
-[Amélie] Granny.
-Oh, my little angel.
You're so clever.
[music continues]
[Amélie] My brother
loved to torture me.
He'd spend whole afternoons
reading comics...
[Andre grunts]
[Juliette shrieks]
[Amélie] ...on top of me.
[music continues]
[Danièle gasps]
[laughs]
-She isn't gonna say your name.
-Oh, like I care anyway.
[Juliette and parents laughing]
Just give her time.
She only knows a few words.
Not true,
I can say a lot of words.
You...you know how to talk?
Yes, I've always known how.
[Patrick laughs]
She speaks like an empress.
What a remarkable child.
She chooses her words.
Stop sulking, young man.
This calls for more champagne.
[laughs]
[Amélie laughs]
[Amélie] Good thing
you were there, Granny.
You were the only one...
-[laughing]
-...who could see the real me.
[Juliette]
I'll miss you, Granny.
You'll come back soon?
Of course.
But next time you'll be so big,
I'll hardly recognize you.
Now look after your parents
because they need it.
Where is Amélie?
[Juliette] Oh, yeah.
I want to say goodbye.
[Patrick] I'll get her,
but hop in the car.
We don't want to be late.
[gentle music]
[Amélie mimics engine]
[gasps] Good heavens!
[continues mimicking engine]
[Granny] What are you doing
here, you little minx?
Where are you going?
The land of white chocolate.
[Amélie laughs]
Oh, I'm going to miss you.
[Granny and Amélie moan softly]
I don't know where she--
oh, there you are.
Come on, Granny's gonna
be late for her plane.
[Granny] Take me away, driver.
Mama, will she be back soon?
Well, not very soon.
She's going to Belgium,
that's far away.
-Across the world.
-[gasps]
Across the world?
-[engine starts]
-I don't want that.
[dramatic music]
It's not fair.
Why doesn't she stay here?
Because she has to go home.
What do you think?
Don't be such a baby.
[Amélie groans]
[Andre shouts]
[Andre grunts]
[Danièle gasps]
Andre, stop fighting.
You too, Amélie.
She almost broke my camera.
-Hey!
-She's just a little kid.
She doesn't know what that is.
[Andre]
Whatever, I didn't ask you.
[Danièle] That's enough.
Both of you go to your rooms.
[Amélie grunts]
[Danièle gasps]
[Amélie crying]
[Andre gasps]
[Amélie]
They didn't understand.
This coarse Belgium may have
given me white chocolate,
but now it was taking
away my grandmother.
The only one who didn't
treat me like a baby.
-[Juliette yelps, pants]
-[Amélie] It was intolerable!
[Juliette shrieks]
[rumbling]
[intense music]
[books thudding]
[Amélie groaning]
[music fades]
[rumbling stops]
[Amélie crying softly]
[book thuds]
[Nishio] I'm a ykai!
[Nishio giggles]
[Amélie laughs]
Look at this.
-[gasps]
-This guy is Otoroshi,
he's a ykai whose job
is to protect the gods.
He's usually found in shrines
that are very remote
and isolated.
When someone does something
bad there, or misbehaves,
he makes the loudest noise
you ever heard!
And he punishes the evildoers
by falling on them
from a great height
-and crushing them.
-[growling]
His job is to teach
humans a lesson.
[anticipatory music]
[heavy footstep thuds]
[monster growls]
[Amélie shrieks]
[music continues]
[licking lips]
[monster growls]
[music ends]
[Nishio laughs]
[gasps]
[Amélie laughs]
-[laughs]
-More, read more.
-There are lots more ykai...
-[Amélie giggles]
...but we'll save them
for next time.
-Wanna help?
-[gentle music]
[Amélie grunts]
Arigato, Amé-chan.
[music fades]
[gasps]
[wood creaking]
[moans softly]
[gentle Japanese-language music
playing in distance]
[coffee drips]
[music continues playing]
[frogs croak]
Nishio-san!
[music fades]
[Amélie blows]
[birdsong]
[upbeat music]
[whispers] Open up.
Open up, everyone! [giggling]
[Amélie] It was my first
springtime ever.
Nature and I awoke together.
[giggling continues]
At my command,
I saw the plants rejoice!
[music continues]
[squeals]
[Amélie squeals, giggles]
[music continues]
[music ends]
[gentle Japanese-language music
playing on radio]
[Amélie giggles]
[music stops]
Nishio-san, Nishio-san!
Why are you out here
on your own so early?
I wanted you to read
about more monsters,
but I left the book
in the kitchen.
[Nishio laughs]
[gentle music]
Then let's go get it.
[music continues]
[grunts softly]
[Amélie panting]
[Amélie laughs]
[giggling]
[Amélie grunts]
[tense music]
[gasps]
Hello, Kashima-san,
it's good to see you again.
I wanted to thank you
for this job.
Hello, Nishio-san.
What's that girl
doing in the garden?
Amélie came looking for me
and found me by the pond.
[Kashima] You don't have time
to waste on her.
Just keep my property in order
by performing the duties
my tenants aren't able to.
That is your job.
Yes ma'am, you're right.
But I'm helping them out
by watching Amélie here.
[humphs]
[Amélie]
She looked so sad, this lady.
Go on home. I'll be right there.
[Amélie]
What was her problem?
Those tight lips
and sinister eyes.
[gentle music]
[Amélie]
The only way to explain it
was that she was
refusing to love me.
She only had to look
at Nishio-san,
who was radiating happiness,
to see that it was good
to love me.
Poor Kashima-san.
I think she suffered
from the disease
of holding back too much.
[music fades]
Ah, Amélie, where were you?
Papa, what is that?
It's a carp.
It's the symbol of boys,
and May is their month.
Why the month of May?
Hmm, I don't know.
Why a month for boys?
Good question.
Which month is for girls?
I, uh, don't think there is one.
[wind blowing]
Well, then why is it a carp?
Why do babies always
have to ask why?
Okay, Papa, I'm done.
All right.
Come on sweetie, let's go.
[Amélie] It was so unfair.
Why a month for boys
and not girls?
Not even a day for girls.
-Not even a symbol.
-[thunder rumbling]
[Amélie]
And again, why a carp?
[rattling]
I want to see a real carp!
-I'm sure we can arrange that.
-[gentle music]
Oh, why don't we ask Nishio-san
where to find some.
[Amélie] I didn't really
wanna leave my sanctuary,
but I had to.
I needed to see a carp
to find out why
they symbolized my brother.
[upbeat piano music]
[music continues]
[music fades]
[Juliette gasps]
It's so beautiful.
[bright music]
Almost there.
[Amélie] So this was it?
The house of carp?
[camera shutter clicking]
[Andre gasps]
[music continues]
-Come on, Juliette, come on!
-[Juliette laughs, pants]
[music continues]
-So where are the carp?
-[Juliette] Papa, come on,
-let's go.
-Hold on. I don't know, sweetie.
[Andre] Look! Look up there.
They're this way,
Amé-chan, over here.
Thanks Nishio-san,
we'll be right there.
[music fades]
Just you wait, some of the carp
are over 100 years old.
[can pops]
[rattling]
[water burbling]
[fish splash]
[gasps softly]
Are you all right?
Bleh!
[fish continue splashing]
Carp are really ugly,
aren't they?
[Nishio laughs]
I can't say I ever
found them very cute.
[Amélie] That's why
they're the symbol of boys
because you're the worst fish.
[heads babbling]
It also might be because they
have long whiskers. [laughs]
[Amélie laughs]
[Amélie] The Japanese
definitely picked
the right fish to symbolize
the uglier gender.
[fish splashing]
Mmnn!
[both laugh]
-[Nishio laughing]
-[Amélie] Bah, bah. Bah.
[Patrick]
Amélie, Nishio-san, let's go.
It's starting to rain!
[Nishio]
We'll be right there.
[thunder cracks]
[gentle music]
Hurry up, Amélie,
or you'll melt!
Aw, can't we stay?
I wanna stand in the rain.
Of course you do,
you are the rain.
The first part of
your name, Amé,
means rain in Japanese.
[Amélie]
My name fit me perfectly.
Like the rain, I was both
precious and perilous.
Benign and deadly.
Silent and tempestuous.
[Amélie raindrops laughing]
[Amélie] But above all,
I felt invincible.
When we get home, I'll show
you how to write your name.
[thunder booms]
[whimpers]
-[Amélie] I was the rain.
-[raindrop giggles]
[Andre] Last one to the kitchen
is a rotten egg!
Woah! Take off those wet socks!
[kids laugh, cheer]
[Juliette] He's the rotten egg.
[Andre]
Nuh-uh, you are. I beat you!
[Juliette]
No you didn't, you cheated!
-[kids shouting indistinctly]
-[Amélie] Show me, Nishio-san.
You said you'd show me how
to write my name in Japanese.
[chuckles]
Maybe we change first?
When we got home
is what you said.
You're right, I did say that.
Now stick your finger up.
-Like that?
-Yes, very good.
Now come close to the window
and let me guide you.
[gentle music]
First draw a horizontal line
like this for the sky.
Then you draw half of a square,
then a vertical line from
the sky to the earth,
and last of all,
four little drops.
And that's how you draw amé,
the character for rain.
I can't really see it.
Hold on.
[Nishio breathes]
[music continues]
-How about now?
-[gasps]
Okay, time to go get changed.
[music continues]
[Amélie breathes]
[Amélie]
I think I'd always known it,
but now there wasn't
any doubt about it.
I was Japanese.
[Patrick sobbing]
[Amélie]
That was the first time
I'd ever seen my father cry.
He looks like a giant baby.
[sobbing continues]
Why are you crying, Papa?
-Are you scared of the storm?
-[both gasp]
[Patrick sobbing]
No, sweetie.
Papa's crying because...
because his mother,
Granny, is gone.
Yeah, she went to Belgium.
No, Amélie,
it's different this time.
Granny will never
be coming back.
She's dead, Amélie.
I'm really sorry.
Dead?
Yes, my angel.
You're too young to understand.
[Andre shouting indistinctly]
Go play with your brother and
sister, I'll be right there.
[kids shouting indistinctly]
[somber music]
[Patrick sobs]
[music continues]
[woman singing in Japanese]
[Amélie]
Death, I knew what it was.
[sobbing continues]
[Danièle] Oh, honey.
[Amélie] But that didn't mean
I understood it.
[music and singing continue
on radio]
[Amélie] My granny had
saved me from death,
and then in no time at all,
it was her turn.
Like it was a trade off
or something.
[music, singing continue]
[Amélie sighs]
But why?
[soft rattling]
[gentle music]
[chuckles]
What is this?
A koma,
that's Japanese for a top.
Try to make yours do that.
[chuckles] Okay, watch.
Like this.
[music continues]
[gasps]
[chuckles]
[man speaking indistinctly
on radio]
Nishio-san, why do we die?
-[knife clatters]
-[stammers] Why do we die?
Um, maybe because...
'cause it's God's will?
God?
I didn't want
my grandmother to die.
What?
Your grandmother's dead?
[Amélie]
Yeah, my mama told me.
Oh, that's terrible.
I had no idea,
Amélie, I'm so sorry.
Why do we die?
Uh, because when
you've lived a good long life,
like your grandmother did,
you get tired.
So you sleep and
that's a good thing.
But don't young people die too?
Yes, well... [exhales]
During the war,
I saw a lot of death.
Tell me about the war.
[chuckles]
Oh, that's ancient history.
You don't wanna hear about that.
I do.
Tell me about it, please.
Okay, then I'll try.
[radio shuts off]
It was long ago.
I was a kid.
I was having breakfast with
my parents and my older sister
when the bombs
started raining down.
[splashing, booming]
It wasn't the first time
for Kobe,
but that day I felt the bombs
were meant for us.
-And I wasn't wrong.
-[metal rattling]
Right next to me,
there was a huge explosion.
[steam roars]
I couldn't believe
I was still alive.
I tried to move
my arms and legs,
but something was stopping me.
It took me a while
to realize I was buried.
[rice clatters]
Strangely enough, I felt safe,
but I began to run out of air.
So I started digging,
digging, digging,
not knowing where I was going.
Then I pricked up my ears.
I told myself that
wherever there was noise,
there would be life.
But I was wrong.
There was only death.
[knife slices]
[exhales]
I lost my whole family that day.
I hope I'm not scaring you
too much with this story.
Were you sad then?
Like my papa?
Yes, but time heals many things,
and the memory of my loved ones
is still fresh with me
and continues
to guide me through life.
Do you still see them?
[Nishio laughs]
[gentle music]
Not the way you see me now.
They walk a different path now,
perhaps becoming
something else altogether.
I picture them and
talk to them sometimes.
It soothes me.
There's a special occasion
coming up.
It's a major event in Japan.
We light candles and
float them down the river,
like for a birthday.
We do it to honor
those we've lost
and to help them on their way.
Can I come and see it?
Maybe.
We'll have to ask your mom.
You can help me
get ready for it.
[gentle music]
How long will Papa
be in Belgium for?
[Danièle] Two months.
They'll go by fast, don't worry.
[engine revs]
[music continues]
[Andre] Come on, try and get it.
-[Amélie] Pass it to me! To me!
-[Andre] You have to get it.
-[Juliette] Here, here!
-[Andre] Juliette!
[Amélie] Over here!
[Andre and Juliette laughing]
[Amélie grunts]
[humphs]
[gentle music playing on radio]
[Amélie blows]
[Amélie chuckles]
[Nishio laughs]
[Nishio blows]
[both laugh]
[gentle piano music]
[both laughing]
Arigato.
[music continues]
[Amélie laughs]
[Amélie grunting]
[Nishio laughs]
[music continues]
[Amélie laughs]
Woo!
[munches]
[giggles]
Mmm!
[Andre laughing]
[music continues]
[Danièle laughs softly]
[hammer clinking]
[blows raspberry]
[shears snip]
[music continues]
[Amélie shouts]
[Andre laughs]
[music continues]
[gasps]
Hey! [laughs]
[music continues]
[giggles]
[Nishio chuckles]
[Amélie grunts, exhales]
[music continues]
[gasps]
[Amélie gasps]
[Nishio chuckles]
You'll bring us some
chocolates, right?
-Hey!
-No, nougat!
-Stop!
-[kids grunting]
-[Patrick] Don't worry.
-[kids shouting]
[Danièle]
Okay, let me talk to Papa.
-[Andre grunts]
-[Juliette] I didn't even
get to talk to him,
thanks a lot, Andre!
[Patrick] Where's Amélie,
is she not there?
Afraid not, Nishio-san
took her down to the river.
You just missed her.
They're setting their candles
on the water.
[Patrick] Ah, that's right.
It's the last day
of the festival.
Amélie so lucky
to get to see that.
Be sure to thank Nishio-san
for taking her.
[Danièle] They love
spending time together.
They're practically
inseparable.
So you're back tomorrow?
[Patrick]
Yes, and I can't wait.
I've been miserable
without you.
When I get back, we'll have
a day at the beach, promise.
[somber music]
[kids laugh]
[music continues]
[match flares]
[Amélie gasps]
[music continues]
[cicadas chirring]
When are we leaving?
Yeah, let's get going.
-Where's Papa and Amélie?
-Patience, ever heard of it?
I wanna stay here with you.
No, you're going to have
a wonderful time.
And besides, your father
just got back from Belgium.
He wants to see you.
But why aren't you
coming with us?
Well, because I've been there.
I went to that beach
with my family.
It was beautiful.
I was a little girl too,
about your age.
I wouldn't want you to miss
standing on
the edge of the world.
[chuckles]
There's my big girl,
I've missed you so much.
[Amélie laughs]
I'll be right here waiting.
Have a good day, Nishio-san.
See you later.
[Nishio] Itterasshai!
[upbeat music playing on radio]
[man on radio] The sun is out,
the skies are clear,
and conditions are perfect
-for a day at Tottori beach...
-[Juliette laughs]
...if you happen to be
out that way.
And now,
to keep things sizzling...
[Juliette]
Don't go anywhere, Papa!
[man on radio]
...is the summer's biggest hit.
[upbeat music]
[Juliette laughs]
[women singing in Japanese
on radio]
[gulls squawking]
[waves crashing]
[laughs]
[music, singing continue
on radio]
[gasps]
[Amélie] I wish Nishio-san
had come with us.
[laughs, pants]
[music, singing continue
on radio]
Mama, can I take this jar?
Jar?
Oh, sure sweetie.
[Amélie laughs]
[music, singing continue]
[squealing]
[squealing continues]
[music, singing continue
on radio]
[ship horn blares in distance]
[water burbling]
[music, singing stop]
[Amélie] Was that
the edge of the world?
Maybe that's where
my grandmother was.
[waves crash]
[ethereal music]
[waves roar]
[music continues]
[sparkling chimes]
[music turns mysterious]
[music swells ominously]
[Amélie gasps]
[water rushing]
[muffled grunting, whimpering]
[gasping]
[water rushing]
Mama!
Papa!
[water rushing]
[mysterious music]
[Danièle pants]
[Amélie coughs]
[parents sigh in relief]
[gentle music]
[Patrick sighs]
[inhales sharply]
Everything's okay now, Amélie.
It was Andre who spotted your
jar abandoned by the water.
[sniffles]
If it hadn't been for him...
[crying softly]
Thank you, Andre.
[sniffles, gasps]
[gasps]
She said Andre.
[Patrick chuckles]
[music continues]
[waves crash]
[metal tinkling]
[rain patters]
[waves crashing]
[gulls squawking]
[music continues]
[rain patters]
[Andre exhales softly]
[snores, exhales softly]
[Amélie]
I looked at my brother
like a mathematical equation.
Without him
there would be no me.
Would I have liked that?
Well, I wouldn't have
been around to find out.
[rain patters]
[thunder rumbles in distance]
[gentle music]
Hi, Nishio-san.
Welcome back.
[car door opens, shuts]
Do you need help, sir?
Sure, if you could
bring Amélie in for us,
that would be great.
-She's had a rough day.
-Of course.
[music continues]
[chuckles softly]
That's a nice jar.
It's for you.
You can open it if you want.
Thank you.
[sparkling chimes]
[whooshing]
[bright music]
[kids laughing]
[whooshing]
[Nishio's mother]
Nishio-san! Oide!
Hayaku oide!
[waves crashing]
[gulls squawking]
[music continues]
[wind whistling]
[Nishio] Arigato, Amé-chan.
[music continues]
[sobs softly]
[sparkling chimes]
[gasps]
Juliette, Juliette,
wake up, it's my birthday!
-I'm three today!
-[Juliette groans sleepily]
[Amélie growls]
[gasps]
[gentle music]
[grunting softly]
[Amélie laughs]
[music continues]
[gasping]
[frogs croak]
[gentle music]
[music continues]
[gasps]
[Nishio]
Good evening, Kashima-san.
-Thank you for having me.
-[Amélie giggles]
[Kashima] It's a little late
for explanations.
[Nishio]
Please forgive me, Kashima-san,
but Amélie takes up
so much of my time.
[Kashima] That's the problem.
She's clouded your judgment.
No, ma'am.
It's just that their family
lost a loved one,
so she was talking
to me about that.
[Kashima] It's not your concern.
Our cultures should not mingle.
[door slides]
[Nishio] I'm sorry, ma'am.
I meant no disrespect.
You showed disrespect
to our ancestors,
taking that girl to the river.
All I've done is
care for a child.
[stones shuffle]
[Kashima] Don't you understand?
Befriending them means
betraying your own.
Have you forgotten
what they did to us?
These people had
nothing to do with that.
I'm only trying to help them
and I love that girl.
[gasps]
How dare you say that
in front of me.
Don't you remember what
they did to us after the war?
They took everything from us.
Everything!
[Amélie thuds and grunts]
[both gasp]
Amélie, what are you doing here?
Um...
Today's my birthday.
[Nishio] Please forgive her,
Kashima-san.
I'll take her back home now.
[exhales sharply]
[Kashima] Come to your senses.
You're too attached
to that child.
The war's over, Kashima-san.
That was 30 years ago.
Her parents were
children themselves then.
My husband!
[somber music]
[breathily] And my son!
Have you forgotten about them?
Your mother, your father,
your little sister.
That's enough.
You're scaring her.
I shouldn't have
asked you to come.
Get out of here.
I never want to see you again.
The child will grow up
one day and forget you.
Just as you have forgotten.
Forgotten everything!
Think carefully whose
side you're on!
Your pathetic attachment to
that girl will come to nothing!
I'm sorry, Amélie.
Nishio-san.
[Amélie] Nishio-san!
Nishio-san!
[sobbing] No!
-Nishio-san, wait!
-Come back!
-Please, Nishio-san.
-[gasps]
Nishio-san, come back!
Nishio-san!
[Amélie sobs]
[sobbing continues]
[Danièle hums comfortingly]
These are grown up problems.
It has nothing to do with you.
[sobbing]
It's Kashima-san's fault.
She was mean to Nishio-san.
They've had to go through
a lot of hardship.
You're too young
to understand yet,
but it doesn't have anything
to do with you, okay?
[Amélie sniffling]
[gasping]
[footsteps approaching]
[Patrick pants]
[somber music]
I am sorry, Amélie.
I couldn't make her stay.
[music continues]
[Juliette panting]
Happy birthday, Amélie!
-Easy, easy, Juliette.
-[Juliette] Mwah!
[Danièle] Yeah, that's right.
We have some candles
to blow out today.
You only turn three once.
We've gotta hurry up,
because we still have
to bake you a cake.
Race you to the kitchen!
[upbeat music]
[Andre]
Move! I wanna take a picture.
[Juliette]
Lemme light the candles.
[camera shutter clicks]
[Patrick gasps]
Knock it off, Andre.
[music continues]
[Juliette] You're so cute.
Papa, Papa!
[giggles]
Happy birthday, honey.
[Patrick chuckles]
[music continues]
[Patrick laughs]
[indistinct chattering]
-[blows weakly]
-[Andre] Can I do it?
[family cheering]
-[Andre] Happy birthday! Smile!
-[camera shutter clicks]
[Juliette] Happy birthday!
[Patrick laughs]
[sighs]
It's time for
your surprise now, sweetie.
[kids giggling]
[gentle music]
[muffled Japanese-language music
plays, fades]
[Danièle] Here, chéri.
[kids giggling]
-[rattling]
-Go on, open it.
[Amélie gasps]
[chuckles]
[dramatic music]
[water burbling]
[fish splash]
-[parents] Surprise!
-[Patrick laughs]
We saw how much fun
you had feeding the carp
at that temple we visited.
So we got you three of them.
One for each year.
[splashing continues]
[Patrick] But now you're
responsible for feeding them
every day
for the rest of their lives.
[Danièle chuckles]
Stop, Patrick,
they can live for
hundreds of years.
[Patrick] Well, until we go
back to Belgium then.
[gasps] Back to Belgium?
Uh, yeah.
We're Belgian,
sweetie, you know that.
No, I'm Japanese.
Sometimes things aren't
the way we want them to be.
Your father works for Belgium,
and if Belgium says that
we have to leave Japan,
then we have to leave.
He doesn't have to
listen to Belgium.
It's so far away!
This is my home, I wanna stay.
No, Belgium's our home, Amélie.
We have to go back.
We belong there, you'll see.
-[dramatic music]
-[Amélie] On that day,
my third birthday,
-everything changed.
-[wind whistling]
I was about to lose
all that I loved.
[music continues]
We're not going right away.
You'll still have time
to enjoy it while we pack up
and get ready to leave.
[Amélie]
Had I done something wrong?
Was I being punished?
Or can things just go away
forever without any warning?
[fish splash]
Would I forget everything?
Nishio-san, my kingdom,
Japan, the flowers, everything?
[music continues]
Is this life?
One great chomping mouth
that spares nothing?
[heartbeat thumping]
[dark music]
[Amélie gasps]
[Amélie] Carpe diem.
[container clatters]
[fish splash]
The day of the carp.
[splashing continues]
[whooshing]
[mouth groaning]
[water burbling]
[soft thud]
[emotional music]
[Amélie] Kashima-san, I began
to understand your sadness.
The sadness of having
lost everything.
I'd never feed the carp again.
I'd never leave Japan.
[water burbling]
[water rushing]
At the age of three,
I went back to the beginning,
to when there was nothing.
[music continues]
[Granny] What are you
doing here, you little minx?
I think I'm dead.
Not quite yet.
Then I'm almost dead
if I'm seeing you.
That's right.
But this is no place for you.
It's so boring here,
and the world is so big.
The world is so sad,
everything goes away.
While I may be gone,
you can still see me
in your memories.
[upbeat music]
[Amélie] If I can't
live in Japan forever,
if I have to lose Nishio-san
and the mountains.
[no audible dialogue]
[Amélie]
If I have to leave the garden,
if what was given
gets taken away,
I have no choice
but to remember.
[music continues]
When we got home
is what you said.
I did say that, you're right.
Okay, stick your finger up.
Like that?
Draw a horizontal line
like this for the sky.
Then you draw...
[continues indistinctly]
Amé.
...and last of all,
four little drops.
[gasps]
Amélie, come back.
[music fades]
[water drop splashes]
[Patrick and Danièle sigh]
[Amélie groans]
[Danièle gasps]
Sweetie, she's awake.
She's awake.
[both gasp]
[Amélie sighs]
Hey, Amélie.
-[Patrick sighs]
-[Andre] You okay?
You've gotta quit
scaring us like that.
[kids giggle]
[Andre]
What's wrong with her head?
Is she hurt bad?
[Juliette] Yeah, is she?
Take it easy, kids.
That's where you bumped
your head in the pond.
Is there a hole?
[Danièle]
Yes, they had to stitch you up.
[Juliette]
Like with a needle and thread?
[Danièle] Yes.
Now be careful, sweetie.
Don't touch that, let it heal.
Someone very special
is here to see you.
[gentle music]
[gasps]
You happy to see her, sweetie?
It was Kashima-san
who saved you.
Kashima-san?
She called Nishio-san,
who came
to the hospital right away.
-[sniffling]
-[Nishio] Amé-chan,
thanks for coming back.
[Amélie cries softly]
You came back too.
Are you gonna stay a while?
I'll stay with you for
as long as you're here.
[continues crying]
[Nishio crying]
[Amélie continues crying]
[Danièle sighs]
[bright gentle music]
[Amélie laughs]
Ah!
[kids shouting]
[both laughing]
[Juliette] I'm not ready yet!
Hold on, give me a minute!
-[Andre] Well, I'm ready!
-[giggles]
[Andre] Come on, hurry up!
[Juliette] Come on, Amélie!
[Amélie laughs]
-[Juliette] Andre! No!
-[Amélie laughs]
[kids shouting indistinctly]
[Juliette] Andre, stop!
Don't hit Mom!
[all laughing, shouting]
Hey, you okay?
[Amélie] When you are three,
you see everything
and understand nothing.
How many swallows does it take
to make a springtime?
Do scars eventually melt away
like snow in the sun?
My dear Nishio-san,
my sunshine, wherever I go,
I'll always remember
the precious years
I spent by your side.
[giggles]
I wanna see and feel everything
as much as one can
in a lifetime...
[laughter]
...and write every page
of my life with passion
and with eyes wide open.
So it turns out I'm not God,
but believe me,
it's a lot more fun this way.
[music continues]
[bright music]
[woman vocalizing]
[music, singing continue]
[upbeat music]
[music continues]
[gentle music]
[music fades]
[water drop splashes]